<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="fullscreen_shell_v2">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2023 Simon Ser

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="wp_fullscreen_shell_v2" version="1">
    <description summary="fullscreen shell">
      This interface provides a mechanism for a client to display simple
      full-screen surfaces.

      This protocol can be used by nested compositors. For instance, a simple
      full-screen compositor might delegate content to a client. Another
      example would be a compositor delegating parts of its content to a
      client, for example drawing a status bar icon might be delegated to a
      client. The compositor dictates the size of the content.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
      phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
      corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
      only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the shell object">
	Destroy the wp_fullscreen_shell_v2 object.

        Other objects are unaffected by this change.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_surface">
      <description summary="obtain a fullscreen surface">
        Obtain a fullscreen surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <description summary="wl_fullscreen_shell error values">
	These errors can be emitted in response to invalid requests.
      </description>
      <entry name="role" value="1" summary="surface has another role"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wp_fullscreen_surface_v2" version="1">
    <description summary="fullscreen surface">
      This object represents a full-screen surface.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the fullscreen surface object">
	Destroy the wp_fullscreen_surface_v2 object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="configure">
      <arg name="serial" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
    </event>

    <request name="ack_configure">
      <arg name="serial" type="uint"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
