<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_toplevel_placement_v1">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 The Wayland Authors

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="ext_toplevel_placement_manager_v1" version="1">
      <description summary="manager to create placement suggestion objects">
        This interface is a manager used to create placement suggestion objects
        for xdg_toplevels.

        The compositor may choose to restrict the availability of this manager
        global or the creation of placement objects via `get_placement`
        to privileged clients based on its internal policy. This policy might involve
        checking the client's identity (e.g., via app_id or executable path)
        against a configured list of trusted clients configurable by the user.
        This is compositor policy.
      </description>

      <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
        <description summary="destroy the placement manager"/>
      </request>

      <request name="get_placement">
        <description summary="get the placement suggestion interface for a toplevel">
            Attempt to create an ext_toplevel_placement_v1 interface for a given
            xdg_toplevel.

            The compositor MUST apply its policy to determine if the client is
            authorized. If the client is not authorized according to compositor policy,
            the compositor MUST send the `permission_denied` error and MUST NOT
            create the object. If the toplevel already has a placement object,
            the compositor MUST send the `placement_exists` error.

            This interface can only be obtained once per xdg_toplevel.
        </description>
        <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_toplevel_placement_v1"/>
        <arg name="toplevel" type="object" interface="xdg_toplevel"/>
      </request>

      <enum name="error">
        <entry name="placement_exists" value="0"
               summary="the toplevel already has a placement object"/>
        <entry name="permission_denied" value="1"
               summary="client is not authorized by compositor policy"/>
      </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_toplevel_placement_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="Interface for suggesting absolute toplevel placement">
      This interface allows a privileged client to suggest an initial placement
      position for its associated xdg_toplevel window, specified using absolute logical
      coordinates relative to a specific wl_output.

      Access to create and use this interface is subject to compositor policy.

      The suggested placement is only a hint. The compositor retains full
      authority to determine the final window position. Clients must
      monitor configure events to determine the actual final placement.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the placement suggestion object"/>
    </request>

    <request name="suggest_position">
      <description summary="suggest placement at absolute logical coordinates on an output">
        Suggests an initial placement position (x, y) for the associated xdg_toplevel.
        The coordinates are in logical pixels, relative to the top-left corner
        of the specified wl_output's logical area.

        This request serves as a hint to the compositor. The compositor MAY ignore
        this hint entirely or modify the outcome based on its state or policies.
        The client MUST NOT assume the suggestion will be honored precisely.

        This suggestion is primarily intended for *initial* placement and should
        ideally be sent before the first wl_surface.commit that maps the window.
        Compositors are unlikely to substantially alter placement based on
        suggestions sent after the window is already mapped and positioned.
      </description>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output" summary="target output"/>
      <arg name="x" type="int" summary="suggested logical x coordinate relative to output"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int" summary="suggested logical y coordinate relative to output"/>
    </request>

    <event name="configured">
       <description summary="notify client of final placement outcome">
         This event notifies the client of the output and logical position where
         the compositor has actually placed the window, typically sent during
         the initial configuration sequence after considering any placement
         suggestions.

         This allows the client to know the result of its suggestion and update
         its stored state accurately. Compositors are not required to send this
         event if no suggestion was made or considered relevant to the final
         placement decision.

         Standard xdg_toplevel.configure events remain the primary source for
         ongoing size, state, and potentially position updates.
       </description>
       <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output" summary="output the window is ultimately placed on"/>
       <arg name="x" type="int" summary="final logical x coordinate relative to output"/>
       <arg name="y" type="int" summary="final logical y coordinate relative to output"/>
    </event>

  </interface>

   <interface name="wl_registry" version="1">
       <request name="bind" type="destructor">
         <description summary="bind an object to the display">
           bind the ext_toplevel_placement_manager_v1 global
         </description>
         <arg name="name" type="uint" summary="unique name for the object"/>
         <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_toplevel_placement_manager_v1" summary="bounded object"/>
       </request>
   </interface>

</protocol>