<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_audio_surface_v1">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2024 Julian Orth

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="ext_audio_surface_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="indicate surfaces playing audio">
      This interface allows clients to inform the compositor which of their
      surfaces are playing audio. The compositor can use this information to
      show corresponding indicators in its UI.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
      phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
      corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
      only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <description summary="ext_audio_surface_manager_v1 error values">
	These errors can be emitted in response to ext_audio_surface_manager_v1
	requests.
      </description>
      <entry name="audio_surface_exists" value="1"
	     summary="the wl_surface already has an extension object"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager object">
	Destroy the manager object. Objects created by this manager are
	unaffected.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="create_surface">
      <description summary="create a new audio surface">
	Create an extension object for a wl_surface to control its audio
	state. If the wl_surface already has an ext_audio_surface_v1, the
	audio_surface_exists protocol error is raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_audio_surface_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
	   summary="the surface to extend"/>
    </request>

  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_audio_surface_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="surface extension object to control the audio state">
      This interface allows the client to inform the compositor when a surface
      is playing audio.

      Each surface is in one of two possible states: started or stopped. By
      default, each surface is in the stopped state, indicating that it is not
      playing audio. The client must make the started request to transition to
      the started state.

      If the surface is destroyed before this object, this object becomes inert.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the extension object">
	Remove the extension object from the wl_surface.

	The surface is automatically reverted to the stopped state. If the
	client wants to synchronize this with a wl_surface.commit, it should
	make a stopped request and commit the surface before destroying this
	object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="started">
      <description summary="the surface has started playing audio">
	Transition the surface to the started state, indicating that it has
	started playing audio.

	It is not an error to make this request when the surface is already in
	the started state.

	The audio state is double-buffered, see wl_surface.commit for details.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="stopped">
      <description summary="the surface has stopped playing audio">
	Transition the surface to the stopped state, indicating that it has
	stopped playing audio.

	It is not an error to make this request when the surface is already in
	the stopped state.

	The audio state is double-buffered, see wl_surface.commit for details.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
