<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="zwp_present_timing_unstable_v1">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2020 Collabora, Ltd.

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="zwp_present_timing_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="timed presentation related wl_surface requests">
      This protocol extension allows an application to obtain per-surface
      presentation properties (e.g. the refresh period), get timing
      information about each present, and to schedule a present to happen
      no earlier than a desired time. An application can use this to
      minimize various visual anomalies (e.g. stuttering).

      This protocol extension is modeled after the VK_EXT_present_timing
      extension.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="">
        Informs the server that the client will no longer be using
        this protocol object. Existing objects created by this object
        are not affected.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_surface_present_timing">
      <description summary="">
        Requests a new zwp_surface_present_timing_v1 object for the given
        surface.

        If the associated wl_surface object becomes invalid, the
        zwp_surface_present_timing_v1 becomes inert and the client should
        destroy it by calling zwp_surface_present_timing.destroy.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zwp_surface_present_timing_v1"
           summary="new surface present timing object"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
           summary="target surface"/>
    </request>

    <event name="clock_id">
      <description summary="clock ID for timestamps">
        This event tells the client in which clock domain the
        compositor interprets the timestamps used by the presentation
        extension. This clock is called the presentation clock.

        The compositor sends this event when the client binds to the
        present_timing interface. The presentation clock does not change
        during the lifetime of the client connection.

        The clock identifier is platform dependent. On Linux/glibc,
        the identifier value is one of the clockid_t values accepted
        by clock_gettime(). clock_gettime() is defined by
        POSIX.1-2001.

        Timestamps in this clock domain are expressed as tv_sec_hi,
        tv_sec_lo, tv_nsec triples, each component being an unsigned
        32-bit value. Whole seconds are in tv_sec which is a 64-bit
        value combined from tv_sec_hi and tv_sec_lo, and the
        additional fractional part in tv_nsec as nanoseconds. Hence,
        for valid timestamps tv_nsec must be in [0, 999999999].

        Note that clock_id applies only to the presentation clock,
        and implies nothing about e.g. the timestamps used in the
        Wayland core protocol input events.

        Compositors should prefer a clock which does not jump and is
        not slewed e.g. by NTP. The absolute value of the clock is
        irrelevant. Precision of one millisecond or better is
        recommended. Clients must be able to query the current clock
        value directly, not by asking the compositor.
      </description>
      <arg name="clk_id" type="uint" summary="platform clock identifier"/>
    </event>

  </interface>

  <interface name="zwp_surface_present_timing_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="">
      An object that allows clients to receive presentation related
      properties for a surface, set presentation timing parameters
      for a present, and request timing feedback for a present.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="unbind from the presentation interface">
        Informs the server that the client will no longer be using
        this protocol object. Existing objects created by this object
        are not affected.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_target_present_time">
      <description summary="">
        Sets the target present time for the next content submission of
        the associated wl_surface.

        The target present time is the earliest time point at which the
        compositor should present the submitted contents. For best results
        on fixed rate displays this should be set to T + n*R, where T is the
        previous content presentation time for this surface, and n*R is an
        integer multiple of the refresh period (see
        zwp_surface_present_timing_v1.timing_properties).

        Note that if a present_slop value has been set, the compositor
        may choose to present earlier than target present time if some
        conditions are met (see zwp_surface_present_timing_v1.set_present_slop
        for details).

        If the target present time is zero or has not been set, this
        extension does not affect the compositor's timings on presenting
        the content submission.

        The target present time is interpreted according to the active clock
        domain (see zwp_present_timing_v1.clock_id).

        The target present time is double-buffered state, and will be applied
        on the next wl_surface.commit request for the associated surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="tv_sec_hi" type="uint"
           summary="high 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_sec_lo" type="uint"
           summary="low 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_nsec" type="uint"
           summary="nanoseconds part of the timestamp"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_ideal_present_time">
      <description summary="">
        Sets the ideal present time for the next content submission of
        the associated wl_surface.

        The ideal present time provides an indication to the compositor
        of what the client desires its presentation duration to become.
        An application the ideal present time to the same value as
        target present time, indicating that the client desires its
        presentation duration to remain steady. A value earlier than
        the target present time that the client desires to shorten its
        presentation duration. A value later than the target present time
        indicates that the application desires to lengthen its presentation
        duration.

        The compositor will provide feedback on this value in the data returned
        in zwp_present_time_feedback_v1. The client can use this information to
        adapt future target present times.

        An unset ideal present time, or a value of zero, indicates no particular
        preference about what the clients desires in terms of presentation rate.

        Setting the ideal present time to timepoint zero, indicates to the
        compositor that no evaluation is needed.

        The ideal present time is double-buffered state, and will be applied
        on the next wl_surface.commit request for the associated surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="tv_sec_hi" type="uint"
           summary="high 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_sec_lo" type="uint"
           summary="low 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_nsec" type="uint"
           summary="nanoseconds part of the timestamp"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_present_slop">
      <description summary="">
        Sets the duration of a time period before the target present time,
        in which the compositor may choose to present the submitted contents
        if it overlaps with the vsync period on fixed refresh rate displays.

        This is used to avoid unintentionally missing a vertical blanking
        period on FRR displays due to rounding errors or drift between
        clocks.

        The present slop is interpreted according to the active clock
        domain (see zwp_present_timing_v1.clock_id).

        The present slop is double-buffered state, and will be applied
        on the next wl_surface.commit request for the associated surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="tv_sec_hi" type="uint"
           summary="high 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_sec_lo" type="uint"
           summary="low 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_nsec" type="uint"
           summary="nanoseconds part of the timestamp"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="refresh_type">
      <description summary="">
      <entry name="fixed" value="0"
             summary="fixed refresh rate"/>
      <entry name="variable" value="1"
             summary="variable refresh rate"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="timing_properties">
      <description summary="">
        The refresh period is an indication of the duration of a present/refresh
        cycle as it applies for the associated surface. The period is interpreted
        according to the active clock domain (see zwp_present_timing_v1.clock_id).

        If presentation occurs at a fixed rate, this is the interval from the start
        of one refresh cycle to the start of the next refresh cycle.

        If presentation may occur at a variable rate (i.e. refresh cycles may
        have variable length), this is the minimum interval from the
        start of one refresh cycle to the start of the next refresh cycle.

        The refresh_type argument indicates whether presentation occurs in a
        fixed or variable rate.

        This event is emitted once the compositor has enough information to evaluate
        the refresh period and refresh type, and whenever these properties change.
      </description>
      <arg name="refresh_tv_sec_hi" type="uint"
           summary="high 32 bits of the seconds part of the refresh period"/>
      <arg name="refresh_tv_sec_lo" type="uint"
           summary="low 32 bits of the seconds part of the refresh period"/>
      <arg name="refresh_tv_nsec" type="uint"
           summary="nanoseconds part of the refresh period"/>
      <arg name="refresh_type" type="uint" enum="refresh_type"
           summary="the refresh type"/>
    </event>

    <request name="feedback">
      <description summary="request presentation feedback information">
        Request presentation feedback for the next content submission
        on the given surface. This creates a new presentation_feedback
        object, which will deliver the feedback information once. If
        multiple presentation_feedback objects are created for the same
        submission, they will all deliver the same information.

        For details on what information is returned, see the
        zwp_present_timing_feedback_v1 interface.
      </description>
      <arg name="callback" type="new_id" interface="zwp_present_timing_feedback_v1"
           summary="new feedback object"/>
    </request>

  </interface>

  <interface name="zwp_present_timing_feedback_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="presentation time feedback event">
      Timing information about a present.
    </description>

    <event name="presented">
      <description summary="the content update was displayed">
        The associated content update was displayed to the user at the
        indicated actual time (actual_tv_sec_hi/lo, actual_tv_nsec).

        The actual timestamp corresponds to the time when the content update
        turned into light the first time on the surface's main output.
        Compositors may approximate this from the framebuffer flip completion
        events from the system, and the latency of the physical display path
        if known.

        The optimal timestamp indicates the time when the compositor would
        have liked the client to set the target present time to. This allows
        the compositor to provide feedback to the provided ideal present time.
        The compositor may set this to the actual present time, to the ideal
        present time (see zwp_surface_present_timing_v1.set_ideal_present_time),
        or to some other time based upon how the client is performing, the system
        load and/or future clock settings.

        All timestamps are interpreted according to the active clock
        domain (see zwp_present_timing_v1.clock_id).
      </description>

      <arg name="actual_tv_sec_hi" type="uint"
           summary="high 32 bits of the seconds part of the actual presentation timestamp"/>
      <arg name="actual_tv_sec_lo" type="uint"
           summary="low 32 bits of the seconds part of the actual presentation timestamp"/>
      <arg name="actual_tv_nsec" type="uint"
           summary="nanoseconds part of the actual presentation timestamp"/>

      <arg name="optimal_tv_sec_hi" type="uint"
           summary="high 32 bits of the seconds part of the optimal presentation timestamp"/>
      <arg name="optimal_tv_sec_lo" type="uint"
           summary="low 32 bits of the seconds part of the optimal presentation timestamp"/>
      <arg name="optimal_tv_nsec" type="uint"
           summary="nanoseconds part of the optimal presentation timestamp"/>
    </event>

    <event name="discarded">
      <description summary="the content update was not displayed">
        The content update was never displayed to the user.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>

</protocol>
