<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="sensitive_content_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 (TBD)

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="protocol to tag areas as sensitive">
    This protocol allows clients to tag wl_surface(s) or wl_region(s), as
    sensitive with a specific type. This tag serves as a hint for the compositor
    to perform actions based on it. Whether the compositor takes action based on
    the tag is compositor policy. By default, compositors should blur, black
    out, or otherwise obscure tagged surfaces and regions in screen captures.
    Additionally, privacy screen features may be toggled based on this tag.
    Features like these should be overridable by the user.

    This document adheres to RFC 2119 when using words like "must",
    "should", "may", etc.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is experimental and may
    change in future revisions. Backward-compatible changes may be introduced
    with a version bump. Incompatible changes require a new major version.
  </description>

  <interface name="wp_sensitive_content_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manages surfaces and regions with sensitive content">
      This interface allows clients to inform the compositor whether they contain
      sensitive information. Each tagged surface or region can include metadata
      describing the type of sensitive content.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager object">
        Destroy the manager object. Objects created by this manager are
        unaffected.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_constructed" value="0"
             summary="the surface or region already has a sensitive content object"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="get_surface_sensitive_content">
      <description summary="create a new surface sensitive content object">
        Create a new sensitive content object associated with a given surface.

        If a surface already has an wp_sensitive_content_v1 attached, the
        already_constructed error must be raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="wp_sensitive_content_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wp_sensitive_content_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="tag a surface or a region as sensitive">
      This interface allows a client to tag a surface or region as sensitive.

      Clients must specify the type of sensitive content (e.g., personal, adult)
      using an enum.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the extension object">
        Destroy this extension object. The surface and all regions will no
        longer be tagged as sensitive and handled as such.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_region" value="0"
             summary="specified region is invalid or out of bounds"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="type">
      <description summary="possible sensitive content types">
        These values specify the type of sensitive content in a tagged surface
        or region.
      </description>
      <entry name="unspecified" value="0">
        <description summary="no sensitive content type specified">
          This value indicates that the content of the area is unknown, or
          unspecified.
        </description>
      </entry>
      <entry name="personal" value="1">
        <description summary="area contains personal content">
          This value indicates that the area contains personal information, such
          as names, addresses, phone numbers, or other personal details.
        </description>
      </entry>
      <entry name="adult" value="2">
        <description summary="area contains adult content">
          This value indicates that the area contains adult content, such as
          violence, sexual content, drugs, gambling, or other adult material.
        </description>
      </entry>
    </enum>

    <request name="set_sensitive_surface">
      <description summary="tag a surface as sensitive">
        Tag a surface as sensitive.

        It is not an error to call this request on a surface already tagged as
        sensitive.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" summary="id associated with the surface"/>
      <arg name="type" type="uint" enum="type"
           summary="type of sensitive content"/>
    </request>

    <request name="add_sensitive_region">
      <description summary="tag a region of a surface as sensitive">
        Tag a specific region of a surface as sensitive.

        The sensitive region is specified in the surface-local coordinates.

        If the specified region is invalid or out of bounds, the invalid_region
        error must be raised.

        The initial value for the sensitive region is empty. Setting the pending
        sensitive region has copy semantics, and the wl_region object can be
        destroyed immediately. A NULL wl_region causes the sensitive region to
        be set to infinite.

        It is not an error to call this request on a region already tagged as
        sensitive.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" summary="id associated with the region">
      <arg name="region" type="object" interface="wl_region" allow-null="false"
           summary="region of the surface to tag as sensitive"/>
      <arg name="type" type="uint" enum="type"
           summary="type of sensitive content"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_sensitive_type">
      <description summary="specify the sensitive type">
        Specify the sensitive type for the surface. This informs the compositor
        that the client believes it is displaying content of this type.
        The client should specify its sensitive type when setting a surface or
        region as sensitive. This request should be called when the client
        believes the content of the surface has changed its sensitive type.

        This serves as a hint for the compositor, which can use it to best
        handle the displayed content.

        The sensitive type is double-buffered state, see wl_surface.commit for
        details.
      </description>
      <arg name="sensitive_type" type="uint" enum="type"
           summary="the sensitive data type"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>