<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_tray_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2024 Julian Orth

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="ext_tray_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="protocol for system tray items">
      This is a global that advertises a tray area. It allows clients to
      displays items in the tray.

      The compositor can advertise multiple globals of this interface. For
      example, if there are multiple outputs with one tray area each. In that
      case, clients that want to display tray items should bind to and use all
      of these globals.

      The compositor can remove this global at any time. For example, when an
      output containing a tray area is disconnected. In that case, the items
      created from the global will no longer be displayed and the client should
      destroy all associated objects.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
      phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
      corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
      only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <description summary="fatal error">
        These fatal protocol errors may be emitted in response to
        invalid requests.
      </description>
      <entry name="conflicting_role" value="0"
             summary="the surface already has another role"/>
      <entry name="already_exists" value="1"
             summary="tray item already exists for the surface"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy this object">
        Destroy this object.

        Created tray items are not affected by this.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_tray_item">
      <description summary="request tray item interface for surface">
        Create a tray item for a surface.

        The surface is assigned the ext-tray-item-v1 role. If the surface
        already has another role, the conflicting_role error is emitted.

        If the surface already has a role object, the already_exists error is
        emitted.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_tray_item_v1"
           summary="the new tray item"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
           summary="the underlying surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_tray_item_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="tray item interface">
      This interface represents an item in a tray. The underlying surface will
      be displayed in the tray.

      Unless the global has been removed, the compositor will immediately emit a
      configuration sequence after this object has been created. If applicable,
      the sequence will also contain wl_surface.preferred_buffer_scale and
      wp_fractional_scale_v1.preferred_scale events.

      After receiving the configuration sequence, the client must ack the
      configuration and commit the surface. The item will not be displayed
      before this.

      The compositor can send configuration sequences at any point.

      If a null buffer is committed, the item will not be displayed.
      If the client wants the item to be displayed, it must ack and commit the
      latest configuration sequence and attach and commit a non-null buffer.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <description summary="fatal error">
        These fatal protocol errors may be emitted in response to
        invalid requests.
      </description>
      <entry name="has_popups" value="0"
             summary="the item has popups at destroy time"/>
      <entry name="has_parent" value="1"
             summary="the popup already has a parent"/>
      <entry name="invalid_seat_serial" value="2"
             summary="invalid serial provided to get_popup"/>
      <entry name="invalid_configure_serial" value="3"
             summary="invalid serial provided to ack_configure"/>
      <entry name="invalid_keyboard_focus_hint" value="4"
             summary="invalid keyboard focus hint provided to get_popup"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy this object">
        Destroy this object. The item is immediately removed from the tray.

        The client must destroy all popups before this. Otherwise the has_popups
        error is emitted.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="ack_configure">
      <description summary="ack a configuration sequence">
        Ack a configuration sequence. The acked configuration sequence is
        double-buffered state, see wl_surface.commit. If the compositor has
        never sent this serial, an invalid_configure_serial error is emitted.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="keyboard_focus_hint">
      <description summary="keyboard focus hint">
        This enum describes when a popup used in the get_popup request should
        get keyboard focus.
      </description>
      <entry name="none" value="0">
        <description summary="no keyboard focus">
          The popup should never get the keyboard focus.
        </description>
      </entry>
      <entry name="on_demand" value="1">
        <description summary="on demand keyboard focus">
          The popup should get the keyboard focus when the user requests it.
        </description>
      </entry>
      <entry name="immediate" value="2">
        <description summary="immediate keyboard focus">
          The popup should get the keyboard focus as soon as it becomes visible.
        </description>
      </entry>
    </enum>

    <request name="get_popup">
      <description summary="create a popup for tray item">
        Create a popup for a tray item.

        The popup should have been created with a null parent. If the popup
        already has a parent, the has_parent error is emitted.

        The seat and serial indicate the interaction that causes this popup to
        be shown. If the compositor has never sent this serial, the compositor
        might emit the invalid_seat_serial error. This is compositor policy.
        If the focus_hint is invalid, the invalid_keyboard_focus_hint error is
        emitted.

        The focus hint indicates how the client wants keyboard focus to be
        handled for the popup. The compositor may ignore the hint. This hint has
        no effect on nested popups.

        The compositor may dismiss the popup at any point.
      </description>
      <arg name="popup" type="object" interface="xdg_popup"
           summary="the popup to be shown"/>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat"
           summary="the causal seat"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint"
           summary="the causal input serial"/>
      <arg name="focus_hint" type="uint" enum="keyboard_focus_hint"
           summary="a hint for keyboard focus handling"/>
    </request>

    <event name="configure_size">
      <description summary="optimal tray item size has changed">
        This event is sent when the optimal size for the item has changed.
        This event is part of a configuration sequence that is terminated with
        a configure event. The client should not act on it immediately but wait
        for the configure event.

        When the client receives this event, it should reconfigure the surface
        for the new size, ack the sequence, and commit the surface.

        If the surface has a different size, the compositor might crop or
        stretch the surface. If the surface has subsurfaces that extend beyond
        the edges of the surface, the compositor might crop them.

        The width and height are at least 1.

        If a configuration sequence does not contain this event, the client
        should assume that the value is unchanged. The first configuration
        sequence must contain this event.
      </description>
      <arg name="width" type="int" summary="the optimal width in surface coordinates"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int" summary="the optimal height in surface coordinates"/>
    </event>

    <event name="preferred_anchor">
      <description summary="preferred anchor has changed">
        This events is sent when the preferred anchor for popup windows changes.
        This event is part of a configuration sequence that is terminated with
        a configure event. The client should not act on it immediately but wait
        for the configure event.

        If a configuration sequence does not contain this event, the client
        should assume that the value is unchanged. The first configuration
        sequence must contain this event.
      </description>
      <arg name="anchor" type="uint" enum="xdg_positioner.anchor"
           summary="the preferred anchor"/>
    </event>

    <event name="preferred_gravity">
      <description summary="preferred gravity has changed">
        This events is sent when the preferred gravity for popup windows changes.
        This event is part of a configuration sequence that is terminated with
        a configure event. The client should not act on it immediately but wait
        for the configure event.

        If a configuration sequence does not contain this event, the client
        should assume that the value is unchanged. The first configuration
        sequence must contain this event.
      </description>
      <arg name="gravity" type="uint" enum="xdg_positioner.gravity"
           summary="the preferred gravity"/>
    </event>

    <event name="configure">
      <description summary="marks the end of a configuration sequence">
        This event marks the end of a configuration sequence. The client should
        act on the new parameters, ack the sequence, and commit the surface.

        Note that this serial is not related to the wl_seat serial used in
        get_popup requests.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
