<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="swapchain_lock_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 Julian Orth

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="protocol for cooperative swapchain exclusion">
    This protocol allows application components to ensure that there is only one
    swapchain for a wl_surface.

    Components using this protocol should ensure that they never

    - make wl_surface.attach requests,
    - create a wp_linux_drm_syncobj_surface_v1 extension,
    - create a wp_commit_timer_v1 extension,
    - create a wp_fifo_v1 extension,
    - create a wp_color_management_surface_v1 extension, or
    - create a wp_color_representation_surface_v1 extension

    for a wl_surface unless they have acquired the lock. Furthermore, they
    should destroy all such extension objects before releasing the lock.
  </description>

  <interface name="wp_swapchain_lock_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="swapchain lock manager">
      A global interface for acquiring swapchain locks.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager object">
        This has no effect on existing locks or lock requests.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="request_lock">
      <description summary="requests the swapchain lock of a surface">
        Requests the swapchain lock of a surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="wp_swapchain_lock_request_v1"
           summary="the request object"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
           summary="the surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wp_swapchain_lock_request_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="advisory swapchain lock request">
      This object represents a request to acquire the advisory swapchain lock
      of a wl_surface.

      Immediately after this object has been created, the compositor will send
      either the denied or the granted event.
    </description>

    <event name="denied" type="destructor">
      <description summary="the request was denied">
        The request to acquire the lock was denied because another lock already
        exists.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="granted" type="destructor">
      <description summary="the request was granted">
        The request to acquire the lock was granted.
      </description>
      <arg name="swapchain" type="new_id" interface="wp_swapchain_lock_v1"
           summary="the acquired lock"/>
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wp_swapchain_lock_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="advisory swapchain lock">
      This object represents the advisory swapchain lock of a wl_surface. While
      this object exists, no other wp_swapchain_lock_v1 can be acquired for the
      wl_surface.
    </description>

    <request name="release" type="destructor">
      <description summary="release the swapchain lock">
        This request destroys the wp_swapchain_lock_v1 object and releases the
        lock.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
