<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_image_capture_request_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 Anna (navi) Figueiredo Gomes

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="request an image source">
    This protocol allows a client to request an ext_image_capture_source_v1
    from the compositor. It allows any clients to acquire a capture source
    without having access to privileged source managers.

    The mechanism used by the compositor to select a source is defined by
    compositor policy. Compositor may choose to render a special selection
    interface, delegate this to a privileged helper by way of the
    ext_image_capture_request_source_v1 interface, return a pre-defined
    source, or implement any policy deemed appropriate.

    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended",  "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
    phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
    corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
    only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
  </description>

  <interface name="ext_image_capture_request_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="request an image capture source">
      This interface is a manager that allows requesting for a image
      capture sources.
    </description>

    <request name="request">
      <description summary="request a source">
        Request an image capture source.
      </description>
      <arg name="request" type="new_id" interface="ext_image_capture_request_v1"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        All objects created by the manager will still remain valid, until their
        appropriate destroy request has been called.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_image_capture_request_v1" version="1">
    <event name="source">
      <description summary="a source was selected">
        This event shall be emitted once a selection has been made.

        After receiving this event, the client must destroy the object.
      </description>
      <arg name="source" type="new_id" interface="ext_image_capture_source_v1"/>
    </event>

    <event name="cancelled">
      <description summary="the request was canceled">
        This event shall be emitted if no selection has been made.

        After receiving this event, the client must destroy the object.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroys the object. This request can be sent at any time by the client.

        Any following response by a matching ext_image_capture_request_pending_v1
        must then be ignored by the compositor.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_image_capture_request_source_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="source for image capture requests">
      This interface allows a privileged client to respond to image copy requests.

      The compositor may choose to restrict this interface to a special client
      launched by the compositor itself, to all privileged clients, expose
      it to all clients, or expose it to no clients at all. This is compositor
      policy.

      If multiple clients bind to this interface, it is compositor policy which
      client responds to any given request.
    </description>

    <event name="request">
      <description summary="an image capture source was requested">
        A client has requested an image source via ext_image_capture_request_manager_v1.request.
      </description>
      <arg name="request" type="new_id" interface="ext_image_capture_request_pending_v1"/>
    </event>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        All objects created by the source will still remain valid, until their
        appropriate source or cancel request has been called.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_image_capture_request_pending_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="pending toplevel request">
      This interface represents a pending request for a foreign toplevel.
    </description>

    <request name="send_source" type="destructor">
      <description summary="provide an image capture source">
        Provides an image capture source. The compositor must follow by
        sending ext_image_capture_request.source on the corresponding request
        with the same image capture source.

        The client must call destroy on the provided image capture source after
        calling this request.
      </description>
      <arg name="source" type="object" interface="ext_image_capture_source_v1"/>
    </request>

    <request name="cancel" type="destructor">
      <description summary="provide no image capture source">
        Cancel the image source request. The compositor must follow by sending
        ext_image_capture_request.cancelled on the corresponding request.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
